我是 Mike，欢迎来到 It's Super Effective
I'm Mike and It's Super Effective
剧透警告
and spoiler alert,
你知道在《洛克人EXE》系列里
did you know that in Mega Man Battle Network,
原话说是“热斗的弟弟”，应该是原作者口误
应当是 Lan's elder brother
洛克人EXE实际上是光热斗的哥哥光彩斗吗
MegaMan.EXE is actually Lan's younger brother Hub?
UP注：HBD
彩斗幼年的时候因为一种罕见的心脏病夭折
Hub died as a baby due to a rare heart complication,
光博士（光裕一郎）决定将彩斗的数据
and Dr. Hikari decided to use his data
变成网络领航员 洛克人EXE
to turn him into the NetNavi MegaMan.EXE.
所以大家来看看
So sit right there,
这些关于《洛克人EXE》系列的事实
this is Mega Man Battle Network facts!
自《洛克人EXE4》起，洛克人系列游戏的销量就开始下滑
Mega Man sales have steadily declined since Mega Man Battle Network 4
EXE4引入了奇怪的多周目要素，每一周目的剧情都是随机的
一些粉丝认为这是对洛克人系列火上浇油
and some fans think that it was the nail in the coffin for Mega Man.
实际上，现在洛克人也仅仅是在其它游戏
In fact, now Mega Man's only cameo appearances are in other games
或是在漫画书里作为客串
and occasionally in comic books.
《洛克人EXE4.5》仅在日本发售
Rockman EXE 4.5 was only released in Japan
EXE4.5里的主角就是你，你可以挑选任何一个你喜欢的角色作为
你的网络领航员
虽然同为《洛克人EXE》系列的世界观
and even though it's set in the same Battle Network Universe,
但和主线剧情完全不同
it doesn't follow the main story line at all.
在EXE1里
In Battle Network here,
电算镇的电影院外的海报说
there's a poster outside the theatre in DenTown that say's
由 Rom Cruze 主演的 Upgrade Impssible 3
"Upgrade Impossible 3" starring Rom Cruze
这明显暗指的是 Tom Cruise 主演的《碟中谍 3》
which is clearly a reference to Mission Impossible 3 starring Tom Cruise.
实际上 EXE4 就出现了
EXE6 里指出了另一款游戏系列叫做《我们的太阳》
Battle Network 6 references another game series called Boktai.
然而《我们的太阳3》没有在日本以外的国家发售
Boktai 3 however wasn't released outside Japan
所以，所有的来自《我们的太阳》的特殊芯片
so all the special chips, the themed chips from Boktai,
然而太阳枪没有被砍掉啊
以及关于《我们的太阳》的支线任务在国际版被移除了
and all the side quests incorporating Boktai have been removed the international versions.
然而在国际版游戏代码里，依然残留着一些关于《我们的太阳》的支线任务的信息
However, in the games code there's still many dialogue
treats and side quests that still reference Boktai in the international versions.
然而他早在光兄弟诞生之前就挂了，是光兄弟的爷爷
光博士的全名是光正
Dr. Hikari's full name Tadashi Hikari
指的是元祖系列的莱特博士
references Dr. Light from the original Mega Man series.
在日本的莱特博士叫做 Right
Dr. Light is named Dr. Right in Japan
而 ただし 一词也被翻译为正
and Tadashi is translated into Right as in just or correct.
EXE 4 里有一些很有趣又经典的语法和拼写错误
Battle Network 4 has some interesting grammar and spelling errors including the classic,
她是多么礼貌的年轻人啊！
"What a polite young man she was!"
EXE 5 也有类似的情况，例如热斗见到名人先生的时候说
Battle Network 5 also has it's share of errors such as Lan meeting Mr. Famous and saying,
名人先生，我在这附近做什么？
"What am I, Mr. Famous, doing around here?"
洛克人 EXE 系列的前三作
In the first three Mega Man Battle Network games,
洛克人的肖像照上显示他有蓝色的眼睛
Mega Man's mugshot shows that he has blue eyes
绿色眼睛是网络领航员普遍的特征：放大一看眼睛还是绿色的
然而他实际上有绿色的眼睛
However, he actually has green eyes
后续几作就纠正过来了
and this was changed in later versions of the game.
洛克人EXE是所有洛克人中
MegaMan.EXE is the only Mega Man in the franchise
把洛克破坏炮装备在右手而不是左手上面的
to have his arm canon on his right arm instead of his left.
洛克人EXE在女性网络领航员中很受欢迎
MegaMan.EXE is blind to his popularity with the female NetNavi's.
实际上，他根本就没注意到萝露和美蒂之间为了和他相处而内斗
In fact, when Roll and Meddy fight over spending time with him he doesn't notice at all,
木头人
他只是认为当她们拥抱他的时候，她们只是表现出友好
and he just thinks when they hug him, they're just being friendly.
在《流星洛克人2》里
In Mega Man Star Force 2,
你可以通过一系列支线任务获得热斗的日记
you can obtain Lan's diary through a handful of side quests.
其中一篇日记指出，热斗的儿子来斗
One of these entries reveal thats Lan's son Patch
拥有他自己的领航员洛克人二世
had his own NetNavi named Mega Man Junior,
结合了洛克人和萝露最佳的特征
which was a program combining all the best qualities of MegaMan.EXE and Roll.EXE.
利卡尔博士的命运在游戏、动画和漫画里完全不同
Dr.Regal's fate changes depending on whether you're
playing the video game watching the anime series or reading the manga.
在 EXE5 的结局里
In the end of Battle Network 5,
他10年来的记忆被灵魂网络所消除
all of his memories from the last 10 years are erased using SoulNet's power
他便以合法身份重新在科学省工作
and he starts fresh as a law abiding person working for Science labs.
在动画里，他被迪奥干掉了
In the anime, he is killed by Duo because of his evilness
《洛克人 EXE Stream》51话
因为他太邪恶了，迪奥将其变成了一具骷髅
and is forcefully aged until there's nothing left but a skeleton.
然而在漫画里，佛鲁迪炸掉了利卡尔博士所在的潜艇
But in the Manga, Bass blows up the submarine with Dr. Regal in it, killing him.
在《参上!飞天小女警 Z》第 19 话里，钢琴怪物里面的玩偶
In Powerpuff Girls Z, episode 19, the doll inside the piano monster
看起来非常像美露
looks a lot like Mayl.
这就是因为她就是以美露为原型的
This is because her appearence was inspired by Mayl.
如果你玩《洛克人 EXE 5 DS 双生领袖》
If you play Mega Man Battle Network 5 Double Team DS,
把不同的 GBA 卡带插到 Gamepak 卡槽会得到不同的额外内容
putting different GBA games into the GBA slot get's you different items.
放入 EXE1-4 和 4.5(日版限定)
Putting Battle Network 1,2,3,4 or 4.5 in,
其实不止，还有很多附加内容
插上 EXE 5 卡带可以将你 EXE 5 本身的芯片夹、改造卡继承过来
如果 GBA 版 EXE 5 有佛鲁迪共鸣洛克人也可以继承过来
你会得到对应游戏的对战音乐
will get you remix battle music from the game that you placed in it.
放入《我们的太阳2》或《我们的太阳3》——如果你玩的是日版
Putting Boktai 2: Solar Boy Django or Boktai 3 in, if you're playing the Japanese version
就会得到太阳共鸣形态
will get you the Sol Cross.
当你打败一个领航员并得到了对应芯片之后
After defeating a Navi and getting it's chip,
当你再次回来跟它对战
if you go back and fight it again
并无伤将对方带走
and take absolutely no damage,
UP注：EXE 3 黑版（美版是蓝版，有对应汉化版）的庞克除外
你还会得到另一张它的芯片
you will receive an extra copy of their chip.
或者是加强版（EX、SP、DS等）
or, occasionally, a battle enhanced version.
如果要在 EXE 1 见到佛鲁迪
To encounter Bass in Mega Man Battle Network 1
不包括 127 号芯片(梦幻灵气) 和 176 号芯片(佛鲁迪)
如果是《流星演习》就需要多集齐 5 张芯片
你就需要集齐 174 张芯片
you're going to need 174 battle chips in your library.
前往互联网 16 区，看到两个领航员并排站到一起
Go to the Internet Area 16 to look at two
men who are standing parallel to each other
在这个地方随便转转，就可以见到佛鲁迪了
keep walking around the area until eventually you will encounter Bass.
实际上，《洛克人 EXE 4》是可以和《洛克人 Zero 3》联动交换到 Z 剑芯片的
汉化版 Zero 3 很可能是基于欧版汉化的，因此你们可能需要相应地拿
欧版 EXE 4 来完成交换。不能跨地区版本交换
在 2003 年，《洛克人 EXE 4》中的常规领航员非常流行
In the summer of 2003, there was a surge in popularity of
the normal NetNavi from Megaman Battle Network 4.
实际上，因为太流行了，相关手办
In fact, it was so popular that toys
和各种周边游戏卖到了3200多万円
and other games occasionally sold up to 32 million Yen.
浦川守的轮椅上有小夜曲的领航员标志
Mamoru Urakawa has an icon of the NetNavi Serenade on the side of his chair.
再强也没洛克人强
我以前一次性对付过三个小夜曲Ω、三个迪奥Ω(EXE4最终BOSS，土豪金)和三个佛鲁迪BX
小夜曲是整个游戏中最强的网络领航员之一
Serenade is one of the strongest Navi's in the entire game,
很显然，小夜曲就是 Bone Bo Uru
and is highly suggested that Serenade is Bone Bo Uru.
而在 Wii U 和 3DS 上的《任天堂明星大乱斗》
In Super Smash Bros, the Wii U and 3DS,
你可以下载 Mii Gunner 套装
you can download a Mii Gunner costume
就可以变成洛克人EXE
which turns out to be MegaMan.EXE.
杰洛是威利博士(元祖系列)制造的
Zero was created by Dr. Wily
UP注：这里使用了 EXE Beast+ 的翻译
图配错了，零之病毒根本不是长这个样子的
威利博士的图也配错了
而零EXE也是威利博士制造的
and Zero.EXE was also created by Dr. Wily
实际上零.EXE本是病毒(零之病毒)
and the fact that Zero.EXE was originally a virus,
很明显就对应到了
is a heavy suggestion that he was the progenitor
来自西叔的∑病毒
洛克人 X 系列的异常者病毒
of the original Maverick virus of the Mega Man X series.
EXE 2 里父母会对其中一个剧情产生争议
Battle Network 2 created some controversy with parents when they found out
有剧情里，亚伊朵对热斗说
that there's a sequence where Yai talks to the main character
这里使用了 EXE 2 汉化版里对应剧情的翻译
“真是不幸啊，热斗。你错过欣赏我优美身材的机会了。”
and says, "if you don't rescue me you might miss out on seeing me naked."
卡婊你到底想做什么？我不需要看未成年女孩的人体艺术……
What is your deal Capcom? I don't need to see underage girls naked.
在 EXE 4 里，热斗床后有一张照片
In Battle Network 4, there's occasionally a poster behind Lan's bed
美露向你竖中指
that has Mayl giving you the finger.
在 EXE 3 黑版(美版是蓝版)里，当你在使用变幻剑的时候按住 A
In Battle Network 3 Blue, if you hold down A while using VarSword
在出现攻击动画之前依次按 上 右 下
and press up, right, and down, before the attack animation happens
就可以得到阔剑的效果
you'll get the WideSword effect.
还可以产生其它剑系的效果
There are other combinations that give you different effects such as
新变幻剑的话还有元素剑，这在秘境网络里进行限时挑战非常重要
比如说长剑、梦幻剑、骑士剑
LongSword, LifeSword, and FighterSword, just to name a few.
在 EXE 3 里，你可以在标题画面集齐七星
In Battle Network 3 as well you can walk seven stars on the main screen after
只要你达到了对应的要求
completing specific objectives.
第六颗星要求打败所有的Ω级别领航员（V4）
The six-star which is red requires you to defeat all 15 Omega Navies.
当你集齐五星的时候，你就在标题画面按下 R R L R L R L L
You must use the code, R R L R L R L L at the title screen once you've acquired 5 stars
第七颗星是把所有的 PA (程序强化，Program Advance) 组合出来
然而并不是随机遇到的幽灵领航员，而是在固定位置
这样就可以挑战Ω级别领航员
to be able to unlock the Omega Navies.
它们是你之前打败的领航员的幽灵
They are ghosts of the Navies that have been previously defeated.
石原裕司说，在《洛克人 EXE 传送》这一作
According to Yuji Ishihara, for Network transmission
本来还打算推出长得像 PET 的定制版 NGC 手柄
there was going to be a GameCube controller released to look like a PET.
UP 主也有一本这个设定集，是日版的
在《洛克人 EXE 官方完整设定集》里甚至还有设定画
There's still concept art available for this in the Mega Man Battle Network Complete Works.
《洛克人 EXE 传送》（美版）里的语音实际上是日语语音、英文字幕
The voice acting in Network Transmission is exclusively Japanese with English subtitles.
然而在英文版里，热斗说“ロックマン”的部分全部被剪掉了
However, in the English version all references to Lan saying "Rockman" have been removed.
口圭，这就是很多关于洛克人 EXE 系列的事实了
Woahhh, that was an awesome load of Mega Man Battle Network Facts.
真的吗？你还有好多不知道的事实呢，让UP主来慢慢跟大家介绍
我真的充分了解了洛克人 EXE 系列
I really dug Battle Network.
当年洛克人 EXE 系列的对战系统甚至还被 CAPCOM 申请了专利
它是非常棒的一种 RPG 系列游戏，有着独特的对战系统
It was a really sweet series of RPG's and a really awesome fighting system.
日本有两款专属的洛克人 EXE 系列游戏，LoN 和 PoN
基于日本专有手机平台 DoJa
因为平台很封闭，想在日本以外的地方玩几乎不可能
我只玩了1和2，我对剧情感到失落
I only played 1 and 2, I kinda fell off cause the story line,
EXE 系列动画非常有趣，最近日本 Kids Station 电视台就在重播第一部呢
和 DVD 生肉版相比，我看到片源之后没发现画质有多大提升
剧情相当的重复累赘
I felt like it was really repetitive
你要把 EXE 当作是一种信仰，我都已经买了四个洛克人的手办了
两个木棉花的、万代的 66 Action 和粘土人
很惭愧，我还没入手千值练手办
我就基本没有玩下去的动力了
and I didn't really feel that engaged anymore
哦！还有一个公仔！我晚上就抱着他睡觉
你们可以脑补一下
不过也还好
but that's okay.
4.5 算好的了，PET 玩具可真是骗钱
除了拿来 cosplay 表演一无是处
我还尝试着玩 EXE 4.5 或者是盗版什么的
I have also however tried to import 4.5 or bootleg it atleast
EXE 动画有粤语版和台湾腔的国语版，不过画质感人
而且……台湾腔听着就特别扭
当然没法玩，毕竟我不懂日文
and it failed miserably and I obviously can't read Japanese, so,
有一种洛克人 EXE 限定版 GBA 主机
作为死忠粉的我已经有入手的打算了
游戏风格完全不一样，插画也很有趣
but it had a different style and the art was really interesting too but
因为《洛克人 EXE 4.5》是为数不多引入了 RTC 的一款 GBA 游戏
只有正版卡带才有 RTC 功能
使用 VBA 模拟器就要求打开“实时时钟”
但是我的主机经常崩溃，这就是生活吧
it kept crashing in my system, so, you know, whatever, that's life.
EXE 和流星系列的文本量巨大，翻译起来非常麻烦
翻译完成后还要排查 BUG
因此洛克人 EXE 系列汉化版做出来非常消耗精力
不管怎么样，在评论区告诉我是否应该重新回顾这个系列
Anyway, tell me whether or not, I should go revisit the series
但是，如果你想回顾的话，我其实建议你玩美版或欧版
虽然某些情况下会砍掉一些内容，但是游戏的主线剧情是不会砍的
或者告诉我你的感受，可以的话就记得订阅
and what your feelings are on it and if you like what you see like, comment, and subscribe
要是英语也不行那就没救了……
现在明白学好英语的重要性了吧
因为它非常有效
Because, It's Super Effective.